Do you know
هل تعلمون
how many species of flowering plants there are?
كم عدد فصائل النباتات المزهرة الموجودة على سطح الأرض ؟
There are a quarter of a million -- at least those are the ones we know about --
هناك مايقارب ربع مليون فصيل .. على الأقل هذه التي نعرفها
a quarter of a million species of flowering plants.
ربع مليون فصيل من النباتات المزهرة !
And flowers are a real bugger.
والأزهار شيء مرهق للنباتات
They're really difficult for plants to produce.
فهي اكثر الاجزاء إرهاقاً للنباتات
They take an enormous amount of energy and a lot of resources.
فهي تستهلك كماً هائلاً من الطاقة والموارد
Why would they go to that bother?
فلم ترهق النباتات ذواتها في إنتاج الازهار ؟
And the answer of course, like so many things in the world,
الجواب حتماً .. كما في كل انحاء الارض ..
is sex.
إنه الجنس
I know what's on your mind when you're looking at these pictures.
اعرف ما يجول في بالكم حين النظر إلى هذه الصور
And the reason that sexual reproduction is so important --
والسبب في كون التكاثر الجنسي مهم ..
there are lots of other things that plants can do to reproduce.
على فكرة .. هناك عدة طرق يمكن للنباتات التكاثر عن طريقها
You can take cuttings;
هناك " القطع "
they can sort of have sex with themselves;
يمكنها ان تمارس الجنس مع نفسها ..
they can pollinate themselves.
يمكنها ان تلقح نفسها ..
But they really need to spread their genes
ولكن الفكرة هي نشر الجينات ..
to mix with other genes
واختلاطها مع جينات أخرى
so that they can adapt to environmental niches.
لكي تستطيع النباتات على الدوام التأقلم مع البيئات المختلفة
Evolution works that way.
ان التطور .. يعتمد على هذه الفكرة
Now the way that plants transmit that information
ان النباتات تنقل معلوماتها ..
is through pollen.
عبر حبات اللقاح
Some of you may have seen some of these pictures before.
والبعض ربما شاهد هذه الصور من قبل
As I say, every home should have a scanning electron microscope
كما قلت .. كل منزل يجب ان يخضع لفحص ميكروسكوبي إلكتروني
to be able to see these.
لكي تستطيعوا ان تروا حبات الطلع هذه
And there is as many different kinds of pollen
وهناك عدة أنواع من حبات اللقاح
as there are flowering plants.
بنفس عدد النباتات المزهرة
And that's actually rather useful for forensics and so on.
وهي - حبات اللقاح - مفيدة في الكشف عن الجرائم أيضاً ..
Most pollen that causes hay fever for us
ان معظم حبات اللقاح التي تصيبنا بحساسية الربيع
is from plants that use the wind
قادمة من النباتات التي تعتمد على الرياح
to disseminate the pollen,
في نشر حبات اللقاح الخاصة بها
and that's a very inefficient process,
وهي عملية فعالة جداً
which is why it gets up our noses so much.
والدليل ان حبات الطلع تصل إلى أنوفنا بكثرة
Because you have to chuck out masses and masses of it,
لان النباتات تنشر كماً هائلاً من حبات الطلع
hoping that your sex cells, your male sex cells,
آملة أن تصل خلاياها الجنسية .. الجنسية المذكرة
which are held within the pollen,
الموجودة في حبوب اللقاح
will somehow reach another flower just by chance.
الى زهرة أخرى من باب المصادفة من اجل التلقيح
So all the grasses, which means all of the cereal crops,
إذا .. كل هذه الحشائش .. وكل حقول القمح ..
and most of the trees
ومعظم الاشجار
have wind-borne pollen.
لديها انواع " طائرة بواسطة الرياح " من حبوب اللقاح
But most species
ولكن معظم الفصائل
actually use insects to do their bidding,
تستخدم الحشرات من اجل التلقيح
and that's more intelligent in a way,
وهي طريقة اكثر ذكاءاً
because the pollen, they don't need so much of it.
لان هذه الطريقة لا تحتاج كماً هائلاً من حبوب اللقاح
The insects
ان الحشرات
and other species
والمخلوقات الاخرى
can take the pollen,
يمكنها ان تنقل حبة لقاح واحدة
transfer it directly to where it's required.
وتنقلها الى المكان المفروض الوصول اليه مباشرة
So we're aware, obviously, of the relationship
لذا نحن على دراية بصورة واضحة عن نوعية العلاقة
between insects and plants.
بين الحشرات والنباتات
There's a symbiotic relationship there,
انها علاقة تكافلية
whether it's flies or birds or bees,
سواء كنا نقصد .. الحشرات او النحل او الطيور
they're getting something in return,
وكل تلك تأخذ شيئاً آخر مقابل قيامها بذلك
and that something in return is generally nectar.
والمكافأة هي رحيق الازهار
Sometimes that symbiosis
ان هذا التكامل
has led to wonderful adaptations --
قد قاد الى نوع بديع من التكيف مع بعضها البعض
the hummingbird hawk-moth
الطائر الطنان ذو المنقار المعكوف هذا ..
is beautiful in its adaptation.
هو احد تلك التكيفات الرائعة
The plant gets something,
هو يأخذ من النبات الرحيق
and the hawk-moth spreads the pollen somewhere else.
والمنقار يحمل بدوره حبوب اللقاح الى مكانها المطلوب
Plants have evolved
ان النباتات تطورت بنحو
to create little landing strips here and there
مكنها من صنع مؤشرات توجيه من اجل الهبوط على اجزاءها
for bees that might have lost their way.
للنحل لكي لا تضل طريقها
There are markings on many plants
انها علامات توجيه موجودة على الكثير من النباتات
that look like other insects.
وتستهدف العديد من الحشرات
These are the anthers of a lily,
هذه نبتة زنبق الأنثير
cleverly done
إبداع حقيقي ..
so that when the unsuspecting insect
عندما تهبط حشرة على تلك
lands on it,
النبتة
the anther flips up and whops it on the back
فإن البتلات ترتفع لتدفع بها الى الداخل
with a great load of pollen that it then goes to another plant with.
وتغرقها بكم كبير من حبوب اللقاح .. لكي تنقل الى نبتة أخرى
And there's an orchid
وهذه الأوركيد
that might look to you as if it's got jaws,
والتي تبدو وكأنها تملك فكين
and in a way, it has; it forces the insect to crawl out,
بصورة ما .. هي تملك فكين .. انها تجبر الحشرة على ان تزحف الى داخلها
getting covered in pollen that it takes somewhere else.
فتغطى بحبوب اللقاح التي تنقل بواسطها الى كل مكان
Orchids: there are 20,000, at least,
ان هناك 20,000 نوع من الأوركيد على الاقل
species of orchids --
ان فصائل الاوركيد ..
amazingly, amazingly diverse.
مميزة .. مبهرة .. متمايزة بروعة
And they get up to all sorts of tricks.
ولقد إبتدعت عدة طرق من الخدع
They have to try and attract pollinators
لكي تجتذب الملقحات - الحشرات -
to do their bidding.
من اجل القيام بعملية التلقيح
This orchid, known as Darwin's orchid,
هذه الاوركيد .. تعرف ب أوركيد داروين
because it's one that he studied
لانها التي اجرى عليها دراساته
and made a wonderful prediction when he saw it --
وبنى عليها افتراضاته عند رؤيتها..
you can see that there's a very long nectar tube
يمكنكم ان تروه هنا انبوب الرحيق الطويل
that descends down
الذي يتضايق نحو الاسفل
from the orchid.
من جهة الاوركيد
And basically what the insect has to do --
ومايجب على الحشرة القيام به
we're in the middle of the flower --
في منتصف الزهرة
it has to stick its little proboscis
على الحشرة .. ان تمد خرطومها
right into the middle of that
الى داخل هذا
and all the way down that nectar tube
ومن ثم عبر انبوب الرحيق
to get to the nectar.
لكي تحصل عليه
And Darwin said, looking at this flower,
وقال داروين معلقاً على ذلك .. بالنظر الى هذه الزهرة
"I guess something has coevolved with this."
" اعتقد ان تطوراً مصاحباً حدث في هذه العملية " - تطور تكافلي -
And sure enough,
وحتماً
there's the insect.
الحشرة كانت جزء منه
And I mean, normally it kind of rolls it away,
عادة ما يكون هذا الانبوب ملتفاً
but in its erect form,
ولكن قد تطور ليبدو بهذه الشاكلة
that's what it looks like.
هذا ما تبدو عليه
Now you can imagine
يمكنكم الآن تصور
that if nectar
كون الرحيق
is such a valuable thing
شيء مكلف .. ومميز
and expensive for the plant to produce
تنتجه النبتة
and it attracts lots of pollinators,
وهذا الشيء المميز يجذب الملقحات
then, just as in human sex,
كما الامر في العملية الجنسية لدى البشر
people might start to deceive.
فإن هناك من يستخدم وسائل الاغراء لاتمامها
They might say, "I've got a bit of nectar. Do you want to come and get it?"
فالنباتات تقول " لدي رحيق مميز .... هل ترغب ببعض منه "
Now this is a plant.
الآن هذه النبتة ..
This is a plant here
هذه النبتة هنا ..
that insects in South Africa just love,
الحشرات في جنوب افريقيا تعشقها ..
and they've evolved with a long proboscis
وقد طورت خراطيم طويلة
to get the nectar at the bottom.
من اجل ان تصل الى الرحيق في الاسفل
And this is the mimic.
هذا تقليد ومحاكاة
So this is a plant that is mimicking the first plant.
هذه النبتة تقلد النبتة الاولى
And here is the long-probosced fly
وها هي الحشرات ذات الخرطوم الطويل
that has not gotten any nectar from the mimic,
ولكنها لم تحصل على الرحيق ..
because the mimic doesn't give it any nectar. It thought it would get some.
لان هذا التقليد .. لا يشمل الرحيق .. الحشرات تتوهم انها ستحصل عليه ..
So not only has the fly
والجميل في الامر .. ليس انها فحسب لن تحصل على الرحيق
not got the nectar from the mimic plant,
من تلك النبتة المقلدة
it's also -- if you look very closely
بل انها ..ان نظرتم جيداً
just at the head end, you can see that it's got a bit of pollen
سوف ترون انه على مؤخرة الرأس .. يوجد القليل من حبوب اللقاح
that it would be transmitting to another plant,
والتي سوف تنتقل الى نبتة أخرى ..
if only some botanist hadn't come along
الا لو كان هناك عالم نباتي
and stuck it to a blue piece of card.
جاء ووضع هذه النقطة على تلك الورقة الزرقاء .. لكي أثبت وجهة نظري
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Now deceit carries on through the plant kingdom.
ان هذا الخداع والإغراء يستشري في كل ممكلة النبات
This flower with its black dots:
هذه الزهرة بالنقط السوداء
they might look like black dots to us,
والتي تبدو لنا نقط سوداء
but if I tell you, to a male insect of the right species,
ولكنها بالنسبة للحشرة الذكر ..
that looks like two females
انها تبدو كحشرتين أنثى
who are really, really hot to trot.
تبدوان بصورة مثيرة جداً
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when the insect gets there and lands on it,
وما ان يهبط الذكر الحشرة على تلك النقاط السوداء
dousing itself in pollen, of course, that it's going to take to another plant,
حتى يتم تعويمه بحبوب الطلع .. والتي سوف تنقل بواسطة الى نبتة أخرى
if you look at the every-home-should-have-one scanning electron microscope picture,
وان نظرتم عبر المجهر الالكتروني .. الذي يجب على كل منزل اقتناءه
you can see that there are actually some patterning there,
سوف ترون بعض الانساق المتمايزة
which is three-dimensional.
هذه صورة بابعاد ثلاثية
So it probably even feels good for the insect,
انها تبدو جميلة .. للحشرات
as well as looking good.
وتشعرها بصورة جيدة على نحو سواء
And these electron microscope pictures --
وهذه الصور المجهرية الالكترونية
here's one of an orchid mimicking an insect --
-هنا صورة لزهرة الاوركيد تقلد شكل الحشرة -
you can see that different parts of the structure
هذه الصور .. توضح لنا البنية المختلفة
have different colors and different textures to our eye,
بألوانها المتمايزة والمختلفة
have very, very different textures
والتي تحوي العديد من الانساق
to what an insect might perceive.
والتي تبدو مغرية للحشرات
And this one is evolved to mimic
وهذه تطورت لتقلد
a glossy metallic surface
سطح معدني لامع
you see on some beetles.
يشابه ذلك الموجود على سطح الخنافس
And under the scanning electron microscope,
وبعد استخدام المجهر الالكتروني
you can see the surface there --
يمكننا ان نرى ان السطح هذا ..
really quite different from the other surfaces we looked at.
مختلف عن السطوح التي نظرنا اليها ..
Sometimes the whole plant
احيانا النبتة بالكامل
mimics an insect, even to us.
تقلد الحشرة .. فننخدع نحن أيضاَ بها
I mean, I think that looks like some sort of flying animal or beast.
اعني .. هذه الصورة تبدو لحشرة طائرة .. او وحش
It's a wonderful, amazing thing.
انها رائعة .. مدهشة ..
This one's clever. It's called obsidian.
هذا تصرف ذكي .. هذه تدعى " أوبيسيدين "
I think of it as insidium sometimes.
احيانا اصفها ب " اينسيديوم"
To the right species of bee,
انها تقلد برسوماتها نوعاً من النحل
this looks like another very aggressive bee,
العدائي الذي يبدو شريراً
and it goes and bonks it on the head lots and lots of times to try and drive it away,
والذي يجول حولك والتي تحاول كثيراً ان تبعده عن رأسك بشتى الطرق ..
and, of course, covers itself with pollen.
وحتماً تغطي نفسها بحبوب الطلع
The other thing it does
والامر الثاني الذي تقوم به
is that this plant mimics another orchid
انها تقليد لزهرة الاوركيد
that has a wonderful store
والتي تكون غنية
of food for insects.
بغذاء الحشرات
And this one doesn't have anything for them.
ولكن هذه لا تحوي أي شيء ..
So it's deceiving on two levels --
انه إذا تخدع\تغري على مستويين ..
fabulous.
أنه امر رائع
(Laughter)
(ضحك )
Here we see ylang ylang,
هذه زهرة " إيالنج إيالنج "
the component of many perfumes.
انها عنصر هام في العديد من العطور
I actually smelt someone with some on earlier.
في الحقيقة لقد كنت مع أنثى تستخدم هذا العطر منذ قليل
And the flowers don't really have to be that gaudy.
ان الازهار عادة لا تحتاج لان تبذل جهداً من اجل اطلاق عطورها ..
They're sending out a fantastic array of scent
انها ترسل طيفاً وسعاً من الروائح
to any insect that'll have it.
تقود الحشرات إليها ..
This one doesn't smell so good.
هذه رائحتها سيئة
This is a flower
هذه زهرة
that really, really smells pretty nasty
رائحتها سيئة جدا جدا جدا
and is designed, again, evolved,
وقد تطورت و انتخبت طبيعياً
to look like carrion.
لكي تبدو مثل " الجيف " - اللحم الميت المتعفن -
So flies love this.
لكي تجتذب الذباب والحشرات
They fly in and they pollinate.
فتطير الحشرات نحوها وتقوم بعملية التلقيح
This, which is helicodiceros,
هذه تدعى " هيليكوديسورس "
is also known as dead horse arum.
كما تعرف بإسم " جيفة الحصان "
I don't know what a dead horse actually smells like,
لا ادري كيف تكون رائحة جيفة الحصان
but this one probably smells pretty much like it.
ولكن يبدو هذه الزهرة لها نفس الرائحة
It's really horrible.
انه مقيتة جداً
And blowflies just can't help themselves.
والذباب لا يستطيع مقاومة هذا الاغراء
They fly into this thing,
فتطير نحوها على الفور
and they fly all the way down it.
وتجد طريقها نحوها على الدوام
They lay their eggs in it,
وتهبط بأرجلها عليها
thinking it's a nice bit of carrion,
حيث تحسبها جيفة
and not realizing that there's no food for the eggs, that the eggs are going to die,
ولا تدرك انه لا يوجد اي طعام لبيضها التي ترغب في وضعه هناك .. والذي عادة ما يموت
but the plant, meanwhile, has benefited,
ولكن النبتة تحصل على مرادها .
because the bristles release
لان اجزائها ما ان تهبط الحشرة تنشر حبوب الطلع
and the flies disappear
ومن ثم ترحل الحشرة
to pollinate the next flower -- fantastic.
نحو زهرة أخرى لكي تلقحها بحبوب الطلع تلك .. انه امر مبدع
Here's arum, arum maculatum,
هذه هي اللوف الأبقع
"lords and ladies," or "cuckoo-pint" in this country.
سيداتي سادتي .. أعيروني إنتباهكم ..
I photographed this thing last week in Dorset.
لقد صورت هذه الصورة في الاسبوع الماضي
This thing heats up
ان هذه النبتة تقوم برفع درجة حرارتها
by about 15 degrees above ambient temperature --
15 درجة فوق درجة حرارة محيطها
amazing.
انه ابداع مميز
And if you look down into it,
وان نظرتم جيداً
there's this sort of dam past the spadix,
سوف ترون انها تشبه جزئيات الطلع المتراصة
flies get attracted by the heat --
ان الحشرات تنجذب نحو الحرارة
which is boiling off volatile chemicals, little midges --
والتي تعمل - الحرارة - على قتل الكيماويات .. هؤلاء الصغار الملاعين
and they get trapped underneath in this container.
يتم حكرهم داخل هذه الحاوية
They drink this fabulous nectar
ويحصلون على الرحيق
and then they're all a bit sticky.
ومن ثم يصبحون " لزقين "
At night they get covered in pollen,
ومن ثم في الليل يتم غمرهم بحبوب اللقاح
which showers down over them,
حيث يتم غسلهم بوفرة بها
and then the bristles that we saw above,
ومن ثم تلك القطاعات التي شاهدتموها في الصورة السابقة
they sort of wilt and allow all these midges out, covered in pollen --
تذبل ويتم تحرير الحشرات التي تحمل حبوب اللقاح
fabulous thing.
انه امر عجيب جداً
Now if you think that's fabulous, this is one of my great favorites.
الآن ان كنتم تظنون هذا عجيب .. انظروا الى هذه
This is the philodendron selloum.
هذه تدعى " فيلونديندورن سيلوم "
For anyone here from Brazil, you'll know about this plant.
واي شخص في البرازيل يعرف هذه النبتة
This is the most amazing thing.
انها نبتة مميزة جداً
That sort of phallic bit there
انها من نوع النباتات القضيبية
is about a foot long.
والتي يبلغ طولها قدم
And it does something
وهي تقوم بأمر مميز
that no other plant that I know of does,
لا تقوم به اي نبتة اخرى
and that is that when it flowers --
اثناء مرحلة الازهار
that's the spadix in the middle there --
في المنتصف يوجد حبوب اللقاح ..
for a period of about two days,
إنه و لمدة يومين ..
it metabolizes in a way
تقوم بعملية إستقلاب
which is rather similar to mammals.
والتي تشابه تلك التي تحدث في الثديات
So instead of having starch,
إذا بدلاً من النشاء ..
which is the food of plants,
والذي هو طعام النباتات
it takes something rather similar to brown fat
فإن هذه تنتج ما يشابه الدهون
and burns it at such a rate
والتي تستخدم في عملية استقلاب
that it's burning fat, metabolizing,
ان حرق الدهون والاستقلاب
about the rate of a small cat.
الذي يحدث يكافىء ذلك الذي يحدث في قطة صغيرة
And that's twice the energy output, weight for weight,
انه الطاقة المنتجة ضعف تلك التي ينتجها
than a hummingbird --
الطائر الطنان المكافىء في الوزن
absolutely astonishing.
انها عملية مبهرة جداً
This thing does something else which is unusual.
انه شيء فريد جداً
Not only will it raise itself to 115 Fahrenheit,
انها لا ترفع درجة حراراتها فحسب الى 115 فهرينهايت
43 or 44 degrees Centigrade, for two days,
43 او 44 درجة مئوية لمدة يومين
but it keeps constant temperature.
بل المبدع انها تحافظ على سوية هذه الحرارة
There's a thermoregulation mechanism in there
يبدو انها لديها نظام مراقبة وضبط حراري
that keeps constant temperature.
والذي يعمل على الابقاء على درجة حرارة ثابتة
"Now why does it do this," I hear you ask.
والآن حتماً تتسائلون لم تقوم بهذا ..
Now wouldn't you know it,
في الحقيقة كما يعلم البعض
there's some beetles that just love to make love at that temperature.
هناك انواع من الخنافس تحب ان تقوم بعملية التكاثر تلك في درجة الحرارة تلك
And they get inside, and they get it all on.
فهي تدخل الى داخل النبتة .. وتمارس الجنس
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And the plant showers them with pollen,
وتقوم النبتة بإمطارهم بحبوب اللقاح
and off they go and pollinate.
وعندما يرحلون يحملون تلك الحبوب معهم
And what a wonderful thing it is.
أليس هذا أمرٌ رائع
Now most pollinators
ان العديد من الملقحين ..
that we think about are insects,
هم من الحشرات
but actually in the tropics,
ولكن في الغابات الاستوائية
many birds and butterflies pollinate.
تستخدم الطيور والفراشات
And many of the tropical flowers are red,
للقيام بنفس الامر .. ان الازهار الاستوائية حمراء
and that's because butterflies and birds
لان الفراش والطيور
see similarly to us, we think,
ترى الامور من حولها بنفس الاسلوب الذي نراه نحن .. هكذا نعتقد
and can see the color red very well.
واللون الاحمر هو لون فاقع واضح للعيان
But if you look at the spectrum,
نحن عندما ننظر الى الطيف الضوئي
birds and us, we see red, green and blue
يمكننا نحن والطيور ان نمايز بين اللون الاخضر والاحمر والازرق
and see that spectrum.
انظروا الى الطيف الضوئي هنا على الشاشة
Insects see green, blue and ultraviolet,
ولكن عندما يخص الامر الحشرات فهي ترى الاخضر والبني ومافوق البنفسجي
and they see various shades of ultraviolet.
وهي ترى طيفاً واسعاً من الالوان فوق البنفسجية
So there's something that goes on off the end there.
وهنا شيء خفي يجري هنا وهناك
"And wouldn't it be great if we could somehow see what that is," I hear you ask.
ولكن أليس من الجميل ان نستطيع نحن أيضاً ان نرى الالوان فوق البنفسجية ..
Well yes we can.
في الحقيقة نستطيع ذلك
So what is an insect seeing?
حسناً لنرى كيف تشاهد الحشرات الحياة !
Last week I took these pictures of rock rose,
في الاسبوع الماضي التقطت هذه الصور في منطقة جبل الزهور
helianthemum, in Dorset.
في " هيلنثاميم في دورسيت "
These are little yellow flowers like we all see,
هذه كما تبدو الازهار الصفراء بالنسبة لنا
little yellow flowers all over the place.
ان هذه الازهار الصفراء تملؤ المكان
And this is what it looks like with visible light.
وها هي كما تبدو مع فلتر الالوان الخفية
This is what it looks like if you take out the red.
انها تبدو هكذا بعد نزع اللون الاحمر الذي لا تراه الحشرات
Most bees don't perceive red.
معظم النحل لا يميز اللون الاحمر
And then I put some ultraviolet filters on my camera
وهكذا تبدو بعد وضع فلتر اللون الفوق بنفسجي
and took a very, very long exposure
وان استخدمنا كاشف عالي الموجة
with the particular frequencies of ultraviolet light
لكي نصل الى تردادات الالوان الفوق البنفسجية
and this is what I got.
نحصل على هذه الصورة
And that's a real fantastic bull's eye.
باتت بديعة الآن
Now we don't know
نحن في الحقيقة لا نعرف تماما كيف تبدو الاشياء للنحل
exactly what a bee sees,
او ما يشاهده النحل حقاً
any more than you know what I'm seeing
في الحقيقة لا نعرف كيف يشاهد النحل الاشياء كما لا نعرف كيف نشاهد نحن الاشياء
when I call this red.
عندما نظن ان شيء لونه احمر
We can't know what's going on in -- let alone an insect's --
فاننا لا نعرف حقيقة انه احمر او لا .. كما في حال الحشرة ..
another human being's mind.
ان دماغنا هو الذي يخبرنا بذلك
But the contrast will look something like that,
على كلٍ .. مع تباين الالون سيبدو الامر هكذا
so standing out a lot from the background.
كما ترون تمايز جيد عن المحيط ..
Here's another little flower --
وهذه زهرة صغيرة أخرى
different range of ultraviolet frequencies,
تملك طيفاً واسعاً من الالوان فوق النفسجية
different filters
باستخدام فلاتر عدة .. هكذا ابدو ..
to match the pollinators.
لكي تشبه الملقحات ..
And that's the sort of thing that it would be seeing.
انه شيء تراه الحشرات فحسب
Just in case you think
ولكي لا تظنوا انه فحسب الازهار الصفراء تملك هذه الخاصية
that all yellow flowers have this property --
فقط دون باقي الازهار ..
no flower was damaged in the process of this shot;
بالمناسبة لم يتم إعطاب اي زهرة اثناء التصوير ..
it was just attached to the tripod,
هذه الزهرة " التريبود " تم تقريبها فحسب للكميرا
not killed --
ولم نقطفها ..
then under ultraviolet light,
هكذا تبدو تحت الضوء فوق البنفسجي
look at that.
انظروا الى هذا ..
And that could be the basis of a sunscreen
انها تبدو كما تبدو الصور من النظارات الواقية من الشمس ..
because sunscreens work by absorbing ultraviolet light.
لان تلك النظارات تمتص الاشعة فوق البنفسجية
So maybe the chemical in that would be useful.
ربما هناك مواد كيميائية تعمل على ذلك
Finally, there's one of evening primrose
في النهاية ختام لهذا الحديث
that Bjorn Rorslett from Norway sent me --
انها صورة ارسلت الي من قبل بجورن رورسليت من النورويج
fantastic hidden pattern.
انه تصميم فني خفي في احدى الزهرات
And I love the idea of something hidden.
وانا احب حينما اكتشف شيء خفي
I think there's something poetic here,
اعتقد ان هناك فن و شاعرية متضمنة هنا
that these pictures taken with ultraviolet filter,
ان هذه الصورة التقطت بواسطة فلتر اشعة فوق بنفسجية
the main use of that filter
ان الهدف الاساسي كان لصناعة ذلك الفلتر
is for astronomers to take pictures of Venus --
هو من اجل رواد الفضاء الذين يدرسون كوكب المريخ
actually the clouds of Venus.
لكي يستطيعوا ان يميزوا سحب المريخ
That's the main use of that filter.
هذا كان الاستخدام الرئيسي لذلك الفلتر
Venus, of course, is the god of love and fertility,
والمريخ ( فينوس ) اسمه اليوناني يعني إلهة الحب والخصوبة
which is the flower story.
وهذه هي قصة جميع الازهار
And just as flowers spend a lot of effort
ولهذا النباتات تبذل كل هذا الجهد من اجل صناعة الازهار
trying to get pollinators to do their bidding,
ومن اجل جذب الملقحات .. ومن اجل عملية التخصيب
they've also somehow managed to persuade us to plant great fields full of them
وهي - النباتات - استطاعت بصورة ما ان تجتذبنا نحن لكي نشارك في تلك العملية
and give them to each other
فنحن نستخدمها
at times of birth and death,
في الولادات .. وفي المآتم
and particularly at marriage,
وفي الزواج
which, when you think of it,
والذي حينما تنظرون اليه من زاوية النباتات
is the moment that encapsulates
فان عملية رمي الأزهار حين العرس
the transfer of genetic material
تبدو وكانها عملية نقل جينية
from one organism to another.
من منظومة حيوية .. تجاه أخرى
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)